Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Has received no answer to his last letter begging for information regarding Mr. Wharton's whereabouts; his reasons for being anxious on this score. Believes it necessary for the tranquility of Europe that America should remain free; attitude of England. Hopes of a Congress being called in Vienna and the American Minister being of the party. Work he has done in connection with electrophorus; notes on some new discoveries about inflammable and explosive air. Cowardly attack on Batavia by the English.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Bersolle, Emmanuel-Yves. Brest
    Has received the packets and, by the first occasion, will forward them to Mr. Holker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Tesché, Pierre Arnoud. Brest
    Offering to supply anything needed in the way of arms; sends list of the various kinds made in his manufactory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 10; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Leyden
    Difficulty of procuring a loan in Holland; mortified at America's lack of credit.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 19; Bigelow, VII, 224).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 11; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Concerning certain bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Equally shocked with Franklin at the consummate artifice and villainy of [Thomas] Digges; sends certain documents which will be proof positive of his guilt; he never applied but £30 of all the money Franklin sent him for the relief of American prisoners. Account of money received and expended by himself on behalf of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 12; A.L. 1p.; ------, -------
    Requesting Franklin to put in a package for Mr. Jay the enclosed letter for Madrid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Kergalec, ----- Riou. Brest
    Concerning certain duties on a cargo of sugar and cocoa brought by an American corsair to Brest; considers them unjust; applies to Franklin for redress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondoire, vicomte de. Rilly
    Concerning cerain moneys due his mother-in-law, Madame d'Admirat, sent from Guadeloupe by her husband, as the proceeds from his sale of sugar in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 16; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Leyden
    After seeing the enclosed letter, amazed at Arnold's daring to show his face among men; his present employment that of stealing tobacco and negroes; Cornwallis engaed in the same pursuit. Has not yet succeeded in negotiating a loan; does not possess one grain of Franklin's faith and hope; motives which prevent the capitalists from coming forward. Desires Franklin's orders how the bills, accepted should be paid. Congratulates him on his success at Versailles. Good results to be expected, should Spain make a treaty with Mr. Jay. If America were willing to be less honest and would threaten to return to Great Britain, all the other Nations would hang themselves to prevent it; Europe's unfair and ungenerous treatment of America; would give millions to have all Europe remain neutral and let England and America fight it out alone.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781] April 16; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Segray, M de
    Sending the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Expressing great pleasure at receiving Franklin's book; inserts a verse written in his honor; begs his presence at the Hotel Girardin, already celebrated by a visit from the Emperor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 18; D.S. 1p.; Potts, William. Passy
    A promissory note for six Louis d'or.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Huquier, A Benoist. Orleans
    Concerning two boxes received from M. Grand, with instructions not to forward them without Franklin's orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume. Châtillon
    If Franklin has no further need of William Penn's letters, asks that he will give them to bearer; desires also a volume of the Philosophical Transactions. Wishes to know if his brother has arrived in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Ferry, -----. Guingamp
    Offers his services to America. If Franklin disapproves of his plan, does not wish his commander, the Prince de Salm [-Krybourg], to know of this offer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 20; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Reply to Franklin's letter proposing a marriage between his grandson and Mlle. Brillon; mentions the inseperable obstacle to such a union.
    Printed in Pumam's Monthly, October, 1906, 36.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Ritchie, Juliana. Cambray
    Asking that the enclosed letter may be forwarded to her husband.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Advices received that the "Romulus," with a convoy of twenty transports, was bound from New York to the assistance of Arnold. Their ships' safe arrival at the Cape to a great market.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1781]; A.L.S. 2p.; Juppin, Mme
    Congratulating him on the successes of the Americans; constantly thinking of him; begs for a line from his grandson with news of his welfare.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de
    Thanking Franklin for the information about M. de Maxwell.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782? April 24; A. Dr. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Notes of a correspondence between Mr. Williams and Mr. Thomas, concerning the shipment of certain merchandise to Messrs. Bache and Shee at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Turgot, Etienne-François, marquis (brother of baron). Paris
    Desires to know the method advised by Franklin for burning smoke and thus diminishing the consumption of wood; thinks this method might be employed in their kitchen stove which burns an immense quantity of wood.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 26; L. 1p.; de Charleville, Gérared Rasquin. Paris
    Petitions Franklin to indemnify him for losses incurred through an order for arms given to him by Mr. Williams of Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Neufville, Leendert de. Paris
    Thanking Franklin for his kind visit, and regretting that he was unable to dine him on Sunday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    His reason for requesting Congress not to make any draughts upon him until he had money to discharge them, His appointment as Minister Plenipotentiary to the States-General; has taken a house in Amsterdam. No chance of credit until their High Mightinesses determine to acknowledge the independence of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Laurens, Martha. Vigan
    Report that her brother, Col. John Laurens, passed through Nantes en route to Paris; their letters to him have remained unanswered; begs for his present address. Her uncle, Mr. James Laurens, [Jr.,] is obliged to set out shortly for England and desires Dr. Franklin to procure him a proper passport, from the French Minister, for Mr. and Mrs.Laurens and the two daughters of H[enry] Laurens, a prisoner in the Tower of London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 30; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Dieffenbach, Philippe
    A native of Alsace; seeks information concerning his cousin, George Mengs, supposed to reside at Philadelphia, also about his uncle, Michel Dieffenbach, an old resident of the latter city. Wishes to know whether his uncle is living or dead and what disposition he made of his fortune.
    (In French. Press copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Des Watines de Flobecq, Louis-Eugene. Saint-Amand
    He and his family are in trouble through the machinations of a wicked young man; begs for Franklin's protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Dana, Francis M. Amsterdam
    Introducing Mr. Warren, son of General Warren of Massachusetts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Lasseray, -----. Paris
    Tug "L'Aimable Elizabeth" cannot leave for Philadelphia for lack of sailors; despatches of la Fayette and Franklin make a speedy departure of importance; asks that influence be used with the Minister of Marine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Willemain d'Abancourt, -----. Paris
    Begs that the enclosed letter be forwarded to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 5; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Has accorded permission that the trunks containing the books be taken to their destination without the usual formalities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 6; A.L.S. 5p.; Gébelin, Antoine Court de
    Grateful for the book, which increases his knowledge of the American languages; has found immense similarity between them and those of the old world; much interested in the vocabulary of the Delawares; has discovered a Phoenician inscription near, south of Boston; thinks they may have been driven by storms on the coast of America. His interest in the American Society of Science and Arts; his plan for establishing a correspondence between the American Society and one lately started in Paris (L'Académie des Inscriptions et Belles Lettres).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 6; A.L. 4p.; Shipley, Georgiana. London
    Delighted with Franklin's "Dialogue with the Gout." Difficulty of procuring a safe conveyance for her letters. Her life in London. News of Sir John Pringle, Dr. Priestley and Dr. Price.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 25; Bigelow, VII, 230).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 7; A.L.S. 2p.; de Bois, Pierre FranÇois. Paris
    Served in the American army; desires to reenter it.
    E. Dr. Franklin requests Col. Laurens to inform him if he is acquainted with de Bois.
    E. Col. Laurens has recollection of an officer of that name but does not know the state of his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 7; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Johonnot, Gabriel and S. Johonnot. Passy
    Accept invitation to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 7; L.S. 1p.; La Lande and Fynje. Amsterdam
    Request that payment of certain bills be stopped.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Watson, Elkanah Jr. Nantes
    Announcing the loss of a small bill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodgson, William. London
    His explanation of Digges's conduct; thinks it unlikely that the money can be recovered; unpleasant stories told of him during his residence in America. Thinks Mr. Trumbull a worthy character. Mr. Jones and Mr. Paradise now members of the club. Money needed for prisoners, if weekly allowance is to be kept up.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 9; A.L.S. James Lovell. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Philadelphia
    Writes on behalf of Mr. Samuel Curson, his partner Mr. Isaac Gouverneur and Dr. John Witherspoon, Jr., taken by the English at the capture of St. Eustatius; cruelty shown to them as well as to Mrs. Gouverneur and her infant; supposed reasons for special severity; their exchange particularly desired.
    (4 copies.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 9; L. in 3d P. 1 p.; Lafreté, Jean-Jacques de
    Begs that his bill of exchange may be accepted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 10; A.N.S. 1 p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume
    Sending Franklin a work by Scheele which had been loaned to Turgot, the Minister, by Franklin and which the writer claimed after Turgot's death.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Mr. Adams's memoir presented to the President of the States-General; will have it published in English, French and Dutch. Reported threats against Holland made by Great Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Monnier de Savignac. Lons-le-Saunier
    Begs for news of his son who is serving with Rochambeau in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Forwards M. Montieu's account; also the protest of the capture made by Capt. Jones, which he begs may be forwarded to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Wesselow, Catherine Cramer de
    Giving an analysis of the character of Franklin's grandson, his progress in his studies and his physical development.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 15; L.S. 3p.; Coulougnac and Cle. Lyons
    Proposition to furnish woolen cloth for uniforms and all kinds of clothing for account of the Congress or individuals in the United States and to sell cargoes coming from that country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Sends a packet which he begs him to forward with his despatches by Mr. [John] Laurens; sorry to trouble Franklin, but Mr. Laurens, from political or other motives, has avoided him.
    Printed in Collections of New York Historical Society, 1889. Deane Papers, IV, 334.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a letter from Dr. Putnam, also some former proceedings of Congress in regard to the sloop which Count D'Arbaud restored to the Governor of Antigua after it had been taken by Dr. Putnam and others.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Vieux Chatellet, ----- L'Ecluze. Quimper
    Desires to serve in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, John
    Mr. Jay declined to receive his oath of allegiance until Franklin's opinion in regard to the propriety of such a step could be learned; begs that an answer be sent to him at Toledo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Watson and Cossoul. Nantes
    The bill in question has been found.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Asking for a passport for his son whom he has determined to send to an Academy near Brussels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 23; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    The news from America not at all bad; has communicated it to all the newspapers. Concerning certain bills ordered by Congress to be drawn upon him, Begs that the enclosed letter, received from Gottenberg, be forwarded to Mr. Jay, with great care as to secrecy and despatch; hopes it will remove all diffculties with Spain, whose accession to the treaty would be of great value to the cause in every part of Europe. Importance to America of obtaining an acknowledgement of their independence from as many Soverigns as possible before conference for peace shall be opened. Suggests acting upon the 10th Article of the Treaty or Alliance. Encloses a memorial of their High Mightinesses. His mission now a subject of deliberation. Discusses Holland's utimate action. All ideas of peace with England false and delusive. Agrees with Franklin respecting duties.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 23; L.S. 1p.; Blome, Otto, baron von
    Recommends an armorer who wishes to emigrate to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    No answers received to his letters of December 2d, February 7th, and April 7th; thinks Franklin's letter was suspected by the authorities and detained in Paris; letters from Dr. Le Bègue de Presle tampered with; directions as to their correspondence in future. His paper upon the theory of the electrophore much enlarged and preceded by an introduction of Franklin's theory of electricity, published in German. Copies of his book sent to Sir John Pringle, Dr. Priestley and other friends. His visit from the Emperor [of Austria] who expressed his regret at not having seen Franklin in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Mazzei, Philip. Florence
    Understood that there was a letter for him from America which Franklin kindly promised to forward; gives address.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Sends translation of Amsterdam's proposal. His intention to write to Congress concerning the difficulties in which his faithful services to the United States have involved him.
    (Partly in French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 25; N. in 3d P. 1p.; De La Brick, -----
    Announcing the birth of a daughter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Paine, Thomas. Brest
    Goes on board in an hour. Hears that Franklin has expressed a desire to withdraw from business; in case his resignation should be accepted, will use any influence in his power to insure its being attended with every mark of honor and consideration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 28; L.S. 1p.; Bersolle, Emmanuel-Yves. Brest
    Has given the packet to Col. Laurens and received the postage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 29; A.L.S. 1p.; des Avranches,-------. Paris
    Recommending Mr. Gleiss, who was acquainted with Franklin in London and wishes to consult him on scientific matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Wendorp, D. and Heyliger, T. Amsterdam
    Concerning their vessel supposed to have been retaken from the English by an American privateer and carried into Morlaix.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Baron, -----. Dunkirk
    Concerning the officers of the frigate "Pallas" who have abused his credit; asking redress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Clifford and Teysset. Amsterdam
    Asks that bills lately remitted for payment to Mr. Isaac Hazlehurst by the Hon. Robert Morris be accepted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781. May.]; A.L.S. 2p.; Turgot,------
    Received his letter and the enclosed engravings. Thanks Franklin for his offer to give him fuller explanations. Intends to have a model of the stove made to introduce its use in ordinary kitchens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Mallet, -----. Havre
    Has received as a boarder a destitute young man called William. Williams who claims to be Franklin's nephew; desires advice in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Talbot, Silas. Plymouth (Mill Prison)
    Commanded the "General Washington" when she was captured by the "Culloden"; his present unfortunate situation in an English prison; begs that fifty pounds be sent him on account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 4; L.S. 1p.; Manley, John. Mill Prison (Plymouth)
    Commanded the "Hancock"; begs for a small remittance. American prisoners, worn out by their long confinement, daily enter the English service; their allowance scarcely provides for one meal a day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 5; A.L.S. 1p.; de Sarsfield, Vicomte. Paris
    Recommending a young man to Franklin who is seeking employment as a secretary. Intends to go to see Franklin before his departure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 6; L.S. 1p.; Chais, -----. Versailles
    Sending a letter to be delivered to Mr. Laurens's oldest son then in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Daran d'Arcaignac, -----. Armentiêres
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Collas, Jane Mecom. Cambridge
    Mr. [John] Thayer has asked for an introduction; is glad of this opportunity to express her appreciation of her Uncle's kindness to Mr. Collas during his imprisonment in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Chantereyne, ----- de. Cherbourg
    Capt. Bennet of the "Franklin" has remitted him the money from the sale of the six ransoms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Brailsford, William. Amsterdam
    Ready to put to sea in a few days; would be honored by any commands from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 9; A.L.S. 6p.; Laurens, John. At sea
    Concerning Franklin's desire to retire from his present important station; suggests the appointment of a Secretary of Legation; qualifications of Franklin's grandson for such a position.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 41; Bigelow, VII, 251).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Conti, Louis-François-Joseph de Bourbon, comte de la Marche and prince de. Paris
    Desiring passports for the grooms who go to England to purchase dogs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Pothonnier and Cie. Paris
    His promise to examine the accounts of the frigate "Alliance," and advise him upon the subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 12; A.L.S. 3p.; de St Hubert, ------. Versailles
    With reference to a geographical and historical dictionary he is going to publish and asking Franklin to suscribe to it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Chew, Benjamin. Nantes
    Appeals to Franklin for assistance to pay his board and lodging whilst waiting for a vessel to take him to America. Will repay the money on his arrival or give a note on his partner Charles Washington of Fredericksburg, Va.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Droüart, Charles-François-Robert (?), seigneur de Lezey, chevalier. Vic
    His letters to his son [Henry Dieudonné Drouart] in Philadelphia seem to miscarry; begs that they may be sent under cover to Franklin's son-in-law [Richard Bache], to whom his son is known. Present occupation unworthy of his birth and lineage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Philadelphia
    Introduces Mr. Cornelius Ray.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Manell, Jean. Dunkirk Prison
    His capture by the English; is an American by birth; desires his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Witherspoon, Jno. Philadelphia
    Writes on behalf of his son, Surgeon on the Letter of Marque, "De Graaff," taken at St. Eustatius and sent to England; encloses a letter of credit for his son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; David, -----. Philadelphia
    His promise to recommend him to Congress to fill the chair of Professor of Anatomy; Dr. Chauvet [Abraham Chovet] his only rival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 15; D.S. Sam[uel] Huntington, President. 3p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Commission of Benjamin Franklin, John Jay, Henry Laurens, Thomas Jefferson and John Adams to negotiate a treaty of peace with Great Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 15; D.S. Sam[uel] Huntington President, and Sealed.; Huntington, Samuel
    Commission of Benjamin Franklin, John Adams, John Jay, Henry Laurens and Thomas Jefferson to accept the mediation of the Emperor of Germany and the Empress of Russia.
    (In triplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Hartley, David. London
    His cousin, Mr. Samuel Hartley, thinks of going to Paris; would like to come himself, provided the French Ministry consent; as a former member of Parliament and an honorable man, desires to do nothing in secret. Conciliatory bill moved by his brother in the House of Commons, in the same form as his own of the year before.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Conyngham, Gustavus. Dunkirk
    Has once more obtained his liberty; hopes for a speedy passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 17; L.S. 2p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Knows nothing of the disposition Mr. [John] Laurens has made of the six millions which the King granted to Congress; suggests that M. de Veimerange might be able to inform Franklin as to these matters; the destination of the funds is also a matter of which he is completely ignorant.
    (In French. Letter press copy in duplicate.)
  - to John Adams., 1781 April 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Laurens, John. Amsterdam